Guide to the W.S. Lewis Collection of W.S. Gilbert Manuscripts and Letters
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
W. S. Lewis collection of W. S. Gilbert manuscripts and letters
1867-1908
GEN MSS 6
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.2
(1 box)
Contains typescript carbon versions of plays by Gilbert, as well as two letters from Gilbert regarding production of, and royalties on, his plays.
Lewis, W. S. (Wilmarth Sheldon), 1895-1979
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of W. S. Lewis, 1942.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of materials pertaining to W. S. Gilbert.
Gilbert, W. S. (William Schwenck), 1836-1911; Lewis, W. S. (Wilmarth Sheldon), 1895-1979
- I. Letters from W. S. Gilbert, 1908 May 29
  - ALS to Mr. Philip Carr, Grim's Dyke, Harrow Weald, 1908 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Enclosing a circular reply which he always sent to applicants who wanted to play his pieces at a reduced price or without a fee at all
  - ALS to Godfrey Reiss, Esq., Grim's Dyke, Harrow Weald, 1908 Jun 02 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Concerning royalty payment
- II. Writings by W. S. Gilbert, [1867]
  - "Allow Me to Explain", [1867] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    A farce; intended for production at the Prince of Wales's Theatre on Saturday, 1867 Nov 2; carbon typescript of the original unpublished manuscript in the Lord Chamberlain's office
  - "Committed For Trial", 1874 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    A farcical comedy in two acts; carbon typescript of original unpublished manuscript in the Lord Chamberlain's office; at head of title: Globe Theatre; originally produced under pseudonym of F. L. Tomline; then re-written and produced under Gilbert's own name
  - "Foggerty's Fairy", [1881] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    An entirely original fairy farce in three acts; typescript of privately printed copy filed in the Lord Chamberlain's office, London
  - "Great Expectations," London, [1871] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Drama in three acts and prologue; Royal Court theatre; carbon typescript of the original manuscript in the Lord Chamberlain's office; "an unpublished play"; adapted from the story by Charles Dickens
  - "Highly Improbable," [London], [1867] (Box 1, Folder 7)
    An origonal impossibility; New Royalty Theatre; carbon typescript of the original unpublished manuscript in the Lord Chamberlain's office
  - "Mountebankes", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Manuscript of the Finale, Act I and a mimeographed copy of the New Finale, Act 1st; with the music; Finale, Act I, signed: Chas. Puerne
  - "Ought We to Visit Her?", [1874] (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Co-authored with Mrs. A. Edwards. Royalty Theatre, 1874 Jan 17; carbon typewritten copy of the original manuscript in the Lord Chamberlain's vaults
  - "Our Island Home" [London], [1870] (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Royal Gallery of Illustration, 1870; carbon typescript of the unpublished manuscript
  - "The Realm of Joy", [1873] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Being a free and easy version of "Le Roe Candeull[!]" (Royalty Theatre, 1873 Oct 18); carbon typescript of the original manuscript in the Lord Chamberlain's office; this play was produced under the pseudonym of F. L. Tomline; the title was later changed to "Realms of Joy"; adapted from Henri Meilhac and Ludovic Halévy's "Le Roi Candaule"
  - "Robinson Crusoe," [London], [1867] (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Co-authored with: Henry James Byron, Thomas Hood, Henry Sambroke Leigh, William Jeffery Prowse, and George Rose; burlesque; carbon typescripts of the original manuscript
  - "Topsy-Turvydom," [London], [1874] (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Original extravaganza; Criterion Theatre, 1874; carbon typescript of the original manuscript in the Lord Chamberlain's vaults